<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>markgo.org</title>
    <link href="https://www.markgo.org/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://www.markgo.org" />
    <updated>2025-05-05T07:25:17+08:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Mark Go</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://www.markgo.org</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Republic Act 12077: Providing Relief on Student Loan Payments During Calamities</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mark Go</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-12077-providing-relief-on-student-loan-payments-during-calamities/index.html"/>
        <id>https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-12077-providing-relief-on-student-loan-payments-during-calamities/index.html</id>
            <category term="Signed into Law"/>
            <category term="Legislative Work"/>

        <updated>2025-05-04T12:08:20+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Republic Act No. 12077, also known as the "Student Loan Payment Moratorium During Disasters and Emergencies Act," is a recently enacted Philippine law approved on December 6, 2024.1 This Act provides much-needed financial relief to students and their families who are grappling with the aftermath&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2> </h2>
<p><strong>Republic Act No. 12077</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">, also known as the "</span><strong>Student Loan Payment Moratorium During Disasters and Emergencies Act</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">," is a recently enacted Philippine law approved on December 6, 2024.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">1</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This Act provides much-needed financial relief to students and their families who are grappling with the aftermath of disasters and other emergencies.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">2</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The core purpose of RA 12077 is to alleviate the financial burden on students with outstanding loans during times of crisis.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">3</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Recognizing that natural calamities and other emergencies can severely impact the capacity of students and their families to meet their financial obligations, the State has mandated a temporary suspension of student loan payments to allow them to prioritize recovery and rebuilding their lives.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">4</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Key provisions of Republic Act 12077 include:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Mandatory Moratorium:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The Act provides for a mandatory moratorium on the payment of all fees, charges, and costs related to student loans.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">5</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Coverage:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This moratorium applies to students enrolled in State Universities and Colleges (SUCs), Local Universities and Colleges (LUCs), private Higher Education Institutions (HEIs), and</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">6</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> public and private Technical-Vocational Institutions (TVIs). The student's residence must be located in a barangay, municipality, city, province, or region under a State of Calamity or State of Emergency as declared by the President of the Philippines or the local sanggunian.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Covered Loans:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The moratorium covers student loans incurred for higher education and technical-vocational education and training (TVET) programs, regardless of whether they are administered by the educational institutions themselves or by government entities such as the Unified Student Financial Assistance System for Tertiary Education (UniFAST) Board or the Commission on Higher Education (CHED).</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">7</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>No Penalties or Additional Interest:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Crucially, the Act stipulates that no penalties, surcharges, or additional interest shall be imposed on the outstanding student loans during the period of the moratorium.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">8</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Duration of the Moratorium:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The moratorium will be in effect for a reasonable period during and after the onset of the disaster or emergency, as defined by the appropriate authorities and the implementing rules and regulations of the Act.</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">By enacting RA 12077, the Philippine government demonstrates its commitment to supporting students and ensuring that their pursuit of education is not derailed by unforeseen crises.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">9</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This law provides a vital safety net, offering temporary financial respite to those most affected by disasters and allowing them to focus on recovery without the added pressure of immediate loan repayments.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">10</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The implementation of this Act is expected to provide significant relief to countless students and families in times of great need.</span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Republic Act 12080: Boosting Mental Health and Well-Being in Basic Education</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mark Go</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-12080-boosting-mental-health-and-well-being-in-basic-education/index.html"/>
        <id>https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-12080-boosting-mental-health-and-well-being-in-basic-education/index.html</id>
            <category term="Signed into Law"/>
            <category term="Legislative Work"/>

        <updated>2025-05-04T12:07:57+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Republic Act No. 12080, officially known as the "Basic Education Mental Health and Well-Being Promotion Act," is a crucial piece of Philippine legislation approved on December 6, 2024.1 Recognizing the growing mental health challenges faced by students and personnel in the basic education sector, this&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2> </h2>
<p><strong>Republic Act No. 12080</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">, officially known as the "</span><strong>Basic Education Mental Health and Well-Being Promotion Act</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">," is a crucial piece of Philippine legislation approved on December 6, 2024.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">1</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Recognizing the growing mental health challenges faced by students and personnel in the basic education sector, this Act mandates the institutionalization and strengthening of mental health services within schools nationwide.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">2</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The primary purpose of RA 12080 is to create a supportive and nurturing environment within basic education institutions that prioritizes the mental health and overall well-being of both learners and school personnel.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">3</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> It aims to ensure that mental health support is readily accessible, destigmatize mental health issues, and equip the school community with the necessary knowledge and skills to address these concerns effectively.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">4</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Key provisions and features of Republic Act 12080 include:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Institutionalization of School-Based Mental Health Programs:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The Act mandates the development and implementation of comprehensive school-based mental health programs in all public and private basic education schools.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">5</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> These programs are intended to promote mental health awareness, provide preventive interventions, and offer support services.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">6</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Establishment of Care Centers:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Every public basic education school is required to establish and maintain a Care Center.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">7</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> These centers will serve as the primary facility within schools for the delivery of mental health services.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">8</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Private basic education institutions are also encouraged to establish and maintain their own care centers.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Creation of Mental Health and Well-Being Offices:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The Act also provides for the establishment of a Mental Health and Well-Being Office in every Schools Division Office (SDO) under the Department of Education (DepEd).</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">9</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> These offices will oversee and support the implementation of mental health programs within their respective divisions.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">10</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Creation of New Plantilla Positions:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> To ensure the availability of qualified mental health professionals in schools, RA 12080 mandates the creation of new plantilla positions within the DepEd for Schools Division Counselors, School Counselors, and School Counselor Associates. This addresses the long-standing shortage of mental health personnel in the education sector and provides a career progression path for these professionals.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Provision of Mental Health Services:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The school-based mental health programs and Care Centers are envisioned to provide a range of services, including mental health screening, evaluation, assessment, and monitoring; mental health first aid; crisis response and referral systems; mental health awareness and literacy</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">11</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> programs; and emotional, developmental, and preventive programs.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">12</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Support for Teaching and Non-Teaching Personnel:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The Act recognizes that mental health support is also essential for school personnel.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">13</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The programs and services extended to them include mental health awareness and literacy programs and appropriate mental health-related referrals.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">14</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Prioritization of Vulnerable Learners:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The Act emphasizes the need to provide tailored support and referral services for vulnerable learners, including children in conflict with the law, those at risk of dropping out, students with disabilities, victims of domestic violence, calamities, and armed conflicts, as well as those who have experienced traumatic experiences.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">1516</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">By institutionalizing mental health programs and providing for dedicated personnel and facilities, Republic Act 12080 marks a significant step forward in prioritizing the mental health and well-being of the basic education community in the Philippines.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">17</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> It underscores the State's commitment to fostering a supportive educational environment where every learner and staff member can thrive emotionally and psychologically.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">18</span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Republic Act 12063: Boosting Filipino Workforce Skills through Enterprise-Based Training</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mark Go</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-12063-boosting-filipino-workforce-skills-through-enterprise-based-training/index.html"/>
        <id>https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-12063-boosting-filipino-workforce-skills-through-enterprise-based-training/index.html</id>
            <category term="Signed into Law"/>
            <category term="Legislative Work"/>

        <updated>2025-05-04T12:05:43+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Republic Act No. 12063, or the Enterprise-Based Education and Training (EBET) Framework Act, is a significant piece of legislation in the Philippines signed into law by President Ferdinand R. Marcos Jr. on November 7, 2024. This Act aims to institutionalize and strengthen enterprise-based education and&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2> </h2>
<p><strong>Republic Act No. 12063</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">, or the </span><strong>Enterprise-Based Education and Training (EBET) Framework Act</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">, is a significant piece of legislation in the Philippines signed into law by President Ferdinand R. Marcos Jr. on November 7, 2024. This Act aims to institutionalize and strengthen enterprise-based education and training programs across the country to address the persistent issue of job-skills mismatch and enhance the employability of the Filipino workforce.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The core purpose of RA 12063 is to create a more cohesive and responsive system of skills development by actively involving private enterprises in the training of individuals.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> By aligning training programs with the actual needs and demands of industries, the Act seeks to ensure that graduates are equipped with relevant and in-demand skills, thereby increasing their chances of securing quality employment and contributing to the nation's economic growth.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Key provisions and features of Republic Act 12063 include:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Institutionalization of the EBET Framework:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The Act establishes a national framework for enterprise-based education and training, rationalizing and harmonizing various training modalities such as apprenticeship, learnership, and dual training system under a unified, competency-based, and industry-driven approach.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Collaboration with the Private Sector:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> A central tenet of the Act is the strong partnership between the government and private enterprises.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Businesses are incentivized to participate in the development of training modules, provide on-the-job training, and contribute to the overall skills development of the workforce.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Addressing Job-Skills Mismatch:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> By directly involving industries in the training process, the Act aims to bridge the gap between the skills taught in educational and training institutions and the actual skills required by employers.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Providing Opportunities for Upskilling and Reskilling:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The EBET framework offers opportunities for Filipino workers to acquire new skills, upgrade their existing competencies, and adapt to the evolving demands of the labor market in a rapidly changing world of work.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Incentives for Participating Enterprises:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> To encourage private sector participation, the Act provides incentives to enterprises that establish and implement TESDA-registered EBET programs.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">9</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> These incentives include additional deductions from their taxable income equivalent to a percentage of their actual training expenses.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Support for Trainees:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The Act also ensures support for trainees by allowing them to avail of scholarships under existing government programs and ensuring that apprentices receive an allowance equivalent to at least 75% of the minimum wage.</span></li>
</ul>
<p>Baguio City Representative Mark Go<span style="font-weight: 400;"> played a significant role in the enactment of the Enterprise-Based Education and Training (EBET) Framework Act.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> As a Co-Chairperson of the Second Congressional Commission on Education (EDCOM 2) and the Chairperson of the House Committee on Higher and Technical Education, he was actively involved in the legislative process that led to the passage of this law.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Representative Go is one of the authors of the bill that became RA 12063. His role in EDCOM 2 and his chairmanship of a key House committee related to education and skills development highlight his commitment to addressing the issues of job-skills mismatch and improving the quality and relevance of education and training in the Philippines. His emphasis on creating a "crucial linkage between training initiatives and industry needs" underscores his understanding of the importance of enterprise-based training in producing a more employable workforce.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The passage of the EBET Framework Act is expected to significantly impact the skills development landscape in the Philippines, fostering a more dynamic and responsive workforce that can meet the challenges and opportunities of the 21st-century economy.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Representative Mark Go's involvement as an author and advocate for this legislation demonstrates his dedication to improving the educational and employment prospects of Filipinos.</span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Republic Act 11192: Establishing the Cordillera State Institute of Technical Education (CSITE)</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mark Go</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-11192-establishing-the-cordillera-state-institute-of-technical-education-csite/index.html"/>
        <id>https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-11192-establishing-the-cordillera-state-institute-of-technical-education-csite/index.html</id>
            <category term="Signed into Law"/>
            <category term="Legislative Work"/>

        <updated>2025-05-04T12:05:02+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Republic Act No. 11192, also known as the "Cordillera State Institute of Technical Education or CSITE Act," is a landmark Philippine law enacted on January 18, 2019. This act is dedicated to rationalizing and strengthening technical-vocational education and training (TVET) in the Cordillera Administrative Region&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Republic Act No. 11192, also known as the "Cordillera State Institute of Technical Education or CSITE Act," is a landmark Philippine law enacted on January 18, 2019. This act is dedicated to rationalizing and strengthening technical-vocational education and training (TVET) in the Cordillera Administrative Region (CAR) by establishing a unified state-run technical-vocational institution.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The primary purpose of RA 11192 is to create the Cordillera State Institute of Technical Education (CSITE) under the supervision of the Technical Education and Skills Development Authority (TESDA).</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">1</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This is achieved by integrating the existing TESDA training centers and TESDA-supervised state-run technical-vocational institutions (TVIs) across the Cordillera region into a single, cohesive institute.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">2</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This integration aims to optimize resources, standardize program offerings, and improve the overall quality and responsiveness of TVET in the CAR.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The establishment of CSITE is seen as a crucial step in developing a highly skilled and competitive workforce in the Cordillera Administrative Region. The Institute is mandated to offer a range of programs, including short-term specialty courses and longer-term technical-vocational education at the technical diploma and national certificate levels.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">3</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> These programs are intended to cater to the specific needs of the region's industries and economy, equipping graduates with employable skills for both domestic and international markets.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">4</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">RA 11192 emphasizes the role of CSITE in providing accessible and relevant technical-vocational education and skills training to students, out-of-school youth, and residents from low-income families, including persons with disabilities, across Baguio City and the provinces of Abra, Apayao, Benguet, Ifugao, Kalinga, and Mountain Province.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">5</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The law envisions CSITE playing a pivotal role in poverty reduction and economic development in the region through skills development and livelihood opportunities.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The integration of existing TESDA institutions under CSITE involves the consolidation of their assets, personnel, programs, and resources. This process, overseen by TESDA in coordination with relevant government agencies and stakeholders, aims to create a more efficient and effective system for delivering TVET in the Cordillera.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The enactment of RA 11192 was a significant legislative achievement for the Cordillera region. Notably, the corresponding House Bill that led to this Republic Act was principally authored by Congressman Mark Go of Baguio City. His advocacy and efforts were instrumental in pushing for the passage of this law, highlighting the importance of strengthening technical-vocational education as a key driver for the region's growth and human capital development.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In accordance with the act, TESDA is responsible for the operationalization of CSITE and the issuance of the necessary implementing rules and regulations to ensure its effective functioning.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">6</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The establishment of CSITE under RA 11192 is expected to lead to a more standardized, accessible, and responsive TVET system in the Cordillera Administrative Region, ultimately contributing to improved employment opportunities and socio-economic progress for its residents.</span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Republic Act 10931: Universal Access to Quality Tertiary Education Act</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mark Go</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-10931-universal-access-to-quality-tertiary-education-act/index.html"/>
        <id>https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-10931-universal-access-to-quality-tertiary-education-act/index.html</id>
            <category term="Signed into Law"/>
            <category term="Legislative Work"/>

        <updated>2025-05-04T12:01:36+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Republic Act No. 10931, widely known as the "Universal Access to Quality Tertiary Education Act," is a transformative Philippine law enacted on August 3, 2017. This landmark legislation has significantly reshaped the landscape of higher and technical-vocational education in the country by institutionalizing free tuition&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Republic Act No. 10931, widely known as the "Universal Access to Quality Tertiary Education Act," is a transformative Philippine law enacted on August 3, 2017. This landmark legislation has significantly reshaped the landscape of higher and technical-vocational education in the country by institutionalizing free tuition and exemption from other fees in eligible public tertiary institutions and providing support for students in private institutions.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The fundamental principle behind RA 10931 is the State's recognition of quality education as a fundamental right and its commitment to making tertiary education accessible to all Filipinos, regardless of their socioeconomic background. The law aims to dismantle the financial barriers that have historically prevented many eligible students from pursuing or completing higher education and technical-vocational training.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A key figure in the legislative process that led to the enactment of this crucial law was Congressman Mark Go, the representative of the lone district of Baguio City. Congressman Go was among the principal authors of House Bill 5633, one of the significant legislative measures in the House of Representatives that was eventually consolidated with other bills to form Republic Act 10931. His authorship reflects his strong advocacy for accessible and quality education, recognizing its pivotal role in individual empowerment and national development.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The salient provisions of Republic Act 10931 include:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Free Higher Education in SUCs and LUCs:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The act mandates that all Filipino students enrolled in courses leading to a bachelor's degree, certificate degree, or any comparable undergraduate degree in State Universities and Colleges (SUCs) and eligible Local Universities and Colleges (LUCs) shall be exempt from paying tuition and all other mandatory school fees. This has opened up opportunities for hundreds of thousands of students across the country.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Free Technical-Vocational Education and Training (TVET) in State-Run TVIs:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Recognizing the importance of technical skills development, the law also provides free tuition and other training-related expenses for Filipino students enrolled in post-secondary non-degree TVET programs offered by state-run TVIs under the supervision of the Technical Education and Skills Development Authority (TESDA).</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Tertiary Education Subsidy (TES):</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Beyond free tuition, RA 10931 established the Tertiary Education Subsidy (TES) to provide financial assistance for education-related expenses, including living allowances, books, and other costs not covered by the free tuition policy. This subsidy is available to qualified students in both public and private higher education institutions and TVIs, with priority given to students from low-income households.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Student Loan Program:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> To further support students, the act created a Student Loan Program for tertiary education, offering another avenue for financial assistance to cover educational costs.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Strengthening of UniFAST:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The law bolstered the Unified Student Financial Assistance System for Tertiary Education (UniFAST), the government body responsible for the overall implementation and management of these student financial assistance programs.</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Congressman Mark Go's involvement as a principal author of the precursor House Bill underscores the legislative drive to prioritize education and expand access to tertiary learning. His work, alongside other legislators, was instrumental in navigating the bill through the legislative process and securing its eventual enactment into law.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While the implementation of RA 10931 has presented some challenges, particularly concerning funding sustainability and the operationalization of the various components, it has undeniably democratized access to higher education in the Philippines. The law stands as a testament to the collective effort to invest in the country's human capital, with legislators like Congressman Mark Go playing a vital role in championing this cause and making quality tertiary education more attainable for Filipino students.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Republic Act 12118: Establishing the Baguio City High School for the Arts</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mark Go</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-12118-establishing-the-baguio-city-high-school-for-the-arts/index.html"/>
        <id>https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-12118-establishing-the-baguio-city-high-school-for-the-arts/index.html</id>
            <category term="Signed into Law"/>
            <category term="Legislative Work"/>

        <updated>2025-03-01T12:11:00+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Republic Act No. 12118, signed into law on January 3, 2025, marks a significant development in specialized secondary education in the Philippines with the establishment of the Baguio City High School for the Arts.1 This Act recognizes the importance of nurturing young Filipino talent in&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2> </h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Republic Act No. 12118, signed into law on January 3, 2025, marks a significant development in specialized secondary education in the Philippines with the establishment of the Baguio City High School for the Arts.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">1</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This Act recognizes the importance of nurturing young Filipino talent in the realm of culture and the arts.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Titled "AN ACT ESTABLISHING THE BAGUIO CITY HIGH SCHOOL FOR THE ARTS AND APPROPRIATING FUNDS THEREFOR," the law mandates the creation of a specialized public high school in Baguio City.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">2</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This institution is designed to offer an arts-focused education, providing a dedicated venue for students with exceptional aptitude and skill in various artistic disciplines to hone their craft within a structured academic environment.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">3</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Baguio City High School for the Arts will operate under the administration and supervision of the Department of Education (DepEd). It is also mandated to work in close coordination with the National Commission for Culture and the Arts (NCCA) and the Cultural Center of the Philippines (CCP).</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">4</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">5</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> collaborative framework aims to ensure that the school's curriculum and programs are aligned with national arts and culture standards and provide students with access to expertise and resources from the country's premier cultural institutions.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">6</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The establishment of this specialized high school is a testament to the State's commitment to fostering the preservation, enrichment, and dynamic evolution of Filipino national culture. By providing specialized training and education, the Act seeks to develop a new generation of artists and cultural practitioners.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">7</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The legislative journey of Republic Act 12118 began in the House of Representatives as House Bill No. 7316.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">8</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The primary author and sponsor of this foundational bill was Congressman Mark Go, the representative of the lone district of Baguio City. His leadership and advocacy were crucial in championing the establishment of a dedicated arts high school in Baguio, a city recognized for its vibrant creative scene and its designation as a UNESCO Creative City. Congressman Go's initiative underscores his commitment to providing specialized educational opportunities that cater to the diverse talents of his constituents and students from the greater Northern Luzon area.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The initial funding for the operationalization of the Baguio City High School for the Arts is charged against the current year's appropriation of the Schools Division Office of Baguio City, with subsequent funding to be included in the annual General Appropriations Act.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">9</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The DepEd, in coordination with the NCCA, CCP, and the local government of Baguio City, is tasked with promulgating the rules and regulations for the effective implementation of the Act.</span></p>
<p><strong>Congressman Mark Go's Role in Republic Acts 11623 and 11624</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Beyond his primary authorship of the law establishing the Baguio City High School for the Arts, Congressman Mark Go also played a supportive role in the enactment of two other significant education-related laws in Baguio City during the 18th Congress: Republic Act 11623 and Republic Act 11624.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Republic Act 11623, enacted on December 10, 2021, is "AN ACT SEPARATING THE BAGUIO CITY NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL – FORT DEL PILAR ANNEX IN BARANGAY FORT DEL PILAR, BAGUIO CITY FROM THE BAGUIO CITY NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL, CONVERTING IT INTO AN INDEPENDENT NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL TO BE KNOWN AS THE FORT DEL PILAR NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL, AND APPROPRIATING FUNDS THEREFOR."</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">1011</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This law effectively converted the Fort Del Pilar Annex into an independent national high school, ensuring it would have its own administration and dedicated funding.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Similarly, Republic Act 11624, also enacted on December 10, 2021, is "AN ACT SEPARATING THE BAGUIO CITY NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL – HILLSIDE ANNEX IN BARANGAY HILLSIDE, BAGUIO CITY FROM THE BAGUIO CITY NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL, CONVERTING IT INTO AN INDEPENDENT NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL TO BE KNOWN</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">12</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> AS THE HILLSIDE NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL, AND APPROPRIATING FUNDS THEREFOR."</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">1314</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This act provided the same independence and dedicated resources for the Hillside Annex, establishing it as the Hillside National High School.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Congressman Mark Go was listed as a co-sponsor of House Bill No. 7994, which led to RA 11623, and House Bill No. 7995, which led to RA 11624. His co-sponsorship of these bills demonstrates his support for the decentralization of large school annexes in his district, aiming to improve their administrative efficiency and ensure they receive adequate resources for the benefit of their students and faculty.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In summary, Congressman Mark Go has been a consistent advocate for educational advancement in Baguio City through his legislative work. His primary authorship of Republic Act 12118 paved the way for a specialized arts high school, while his co-sponsorship of the bills that became Republic Acts 11623 and 11624 contributed to the establishment of independent national high schools from former annexes, all aimed at providing better educational opportunities for the youth in his district.</span></p>
<p><br><br></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Republic Act 12119: Establishing the Baguio City Sports High School</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mark Go</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-12119-establishing-the-baguio-city-sports-high-school-championed-by-congressman-mark-go/index.html"/>
        <id>https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-12119-establishing-the-baguio-city-sports-high-school-championed-by-congressman-mark-go/index.html</id>
            <category term="Signed into Law"/>
            <category term="Legislative Work"/>

        <updated>2025-01-03T12:10:00+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Republic Act No. 12119, signed into law on January 3, 2025, is a significant legislative achievement for the development of sports in the Philippines, particularly in the Cordillera Administrative Region. Titled "AN ACT ESTABLISHING THE BAGUIO CITY SPORTS HIGH SCHOOL AND APPROPRIATING FUNDS THEREFOR," this&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2> </h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>Republic Act No. 12119</strong>, signed into law on January 3, 2025, is a significant legislative achievement for the development of sports in the Philippines, particularly in the Cordillera Administrative Region.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Titled "<em><strong>AN ACT ESTABLISHING THE BAGUIO CITY SPORTS HIGH SCHOOL AND APPROPRIATING FUNDS THEREFOR</strong></em>," this law paves the way for the creation of a specialized public high school in Baguio City dedicated to nurturing young Filipino athletes.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The core principle of RA 12119 is the State's commitment to promoting physical education and sports programs to foster self-discipline, teamwork, and excellence. The Act aims to provide a dedicated educational institution that combines a standard secondary education curriculum with intensive sports training for students who have demonstrated considerable potential in various sports disciplines.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Key provisions of Republic Act 12119 include:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Establishment of the Baguio City Sports High School:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The law mandates the creation of a specialized public high school in Baguio City that will offer a sports-focused education program.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Integrated Curriculum:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The school will implement the general secondary education curriculum as prescribed by the Enhanced Basic Education Act of 2013 (RA 10533), with a significant emphasis on developing the athletic skills of learners through specialized subjects in physical education and sports.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Coordination with Sports Authorities:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The school will be administered and supervised by the Department of Education (DepEd) in close coordination with the Philippine Sports Commission</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">5</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> (PSC) and the National Academy of Sports (NAS).</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This collaboration is intended to ensure that the sports programs are aligned with national sports development goals and standards.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Funding:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The initial funding for the operationalization of the Baguio City Sports High School will be charged against the current year's appropriation of the Schools Division Office of Baguio City, with subsequent funding to be included in the annual General Appropriations Act.</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The establishment of the Baguio City Sports High School is expected to provide a clear pathway for talented young athletes in Baguio and the broader Northern Luzon area to receive quality education while simultaneously developing their athletic prowess.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">9</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This specialized training is crucial for producing future national athletes who can represent the country in various competitions.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The legislative effort behind Republic Act 12119 was notably led by Congressman Mark Go, the representative of the lone district of Baguio City. He served as the primary author and sponsor of House Bill No. 8700, the precursor to this Republic Act in the House of Representatives. Congressman Go's strong advocacy for sports development and his commitment to providing specialized educational opportunities for the youth of Baguio were instrumental in the passage of this law. His initiative reflects a vision to harness the athletic potential of young Filipinos and provide them with the necessary support and training to excel in their chosen sports.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The enactment of RA 12119, alongside RA 12118 establishing the Baguio City High School for the Arts (which Congressman Go also primarily authored), signifies a concerted effort to provide specialized educational institutions in Baguio City that cater to the diverse talents and potentials of students in the region.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">10</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Congressman Go's role as the primary author and sponsor of both these landmark laws underscores his dedication to enhancing the educational landscape and providing unique opportunities for the youth in his constituency.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Department of Education, in coordination with the PSC, NAS, and the local government of Baguio City, is tasked with formulating the implementing rules and regulations for RA 12119 to ensure the effective organization, administration, operations, and management of the Baguio City Sports High School.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">11</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This will be crucial in translating the vision of the law into tangible opportunities for aspiring young athletes.</span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Republic Act 11984: Ending the &quot;No Permit, No Exam&quot; Policy for Disadvantaged Students</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mark Go</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-11984-ending-the-no-permit-no-exam-policy-for-disadvantaged-students/index.html"/>
        <id>https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-11984-ending-the-no-permit-no-exam-policy-for-disadvantaged-students/index.html</id>
            <category term="Signed into Law"/>
            <category term="Legislative Work"/>

        <updated>2024-03-11T12:08:00+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Republic Act No. 11984, officially titled the "No Permit, No Exam Prohibition Act," is a significant piece of legislation in the Philippines that was approved on March 11, 2024.1 This Act directly addresses a long-standing issue in the Philippine education system where students with unsettled&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2> </h2>
<p><strong>Republic Act No. 11984</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">, officially titled the "</span><strong>No Permit, No Exam Prohibition Act</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">," is a significant piece of legislation in the Philippines that was approved on March 11, 2024.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">1</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This Act directly addresses a long-standing issue in the Philippine education system where students with unsettled tuition and other school fees are barred from taking their periodic and final examinations.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The core purpose of RA 11984 is to protect and promote the right of disadvantaged students to quality education by ensuring that their inability to immediately pay their school fees does not become a barrier to taking scheduled examinations.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The State recognizes the importance of education and aims to make it more accessible, particularly for those facing financial difficulties.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Key provisions of Republic Act 11984 include:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Prohibition of the "No Permit, No Exam" Policy:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The Act explicitly prohibits all public and private educational institutions, including basic education (K to 12), higher education institutions (HEIs), and technical-vocational institutions (TVIs) offering long-term courses (exceeding one year), from preventing disadvantaged students with unpaid tuition and other school fees from taking their periodic and final examinations.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Mandate to Accommodate Disadvantaged Students:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Educational institutions covered by the Act are mandated to accommodate and allow these disadvantaged students to take their examinations without requiring a permit. For K to 12 students, this mandate applies for the entire school year.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Definition of "Disadvantaged Student":</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The Act directs the Department of Social Welfare and Development (DSWD), in consultation with relevant stakeholders, to promulgate the rules and regulations that will define what constitutes a "Disadvantaged Student" and the criteria and requirements for the issuance of a certification to that effect by the appropriate local social welfare development officer.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This aims to provide a clear basis for identifying students covered by the Act.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Administrative Sanctions:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Educational institutions found violating the provisions of the Act will be subject to administrative sanctions imposed by the relevant government agencies, namely the Department of Education (DepEd), the Commission on Higher Education (CHED), and the Technical Education and Skills Development Authority (TESDA),</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> as the case may be.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Preservation of Institutions' Right to Collect Fees:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> While the Act prohibits barring students from exams, it clarifies that it is without prejudice to the right and power of educational institutions to require the submission of a promissory note, withhold</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> the release of student records and credentials, and pursue other legal and administrative remedies to collect unpaid fees.</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In essence, Republic Act 11984 provides a legal safety net for disadvantaged students, ensuring that they are not denied the opportunity to be assessed academically solely due to financial constraints at the time of examinations.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> It reinforces the constitutional right to education and emphasizes compassion and understanding for students facing economic hardships, while still acknowledging the right of educational institutions to seek payment of arrears through other legitimate means.</span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Republic Act 11982: Expanding Benefits for Elderly Filipinos, with Congressman Mark Go as Author</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mark Go</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-11982-expanding-benefits-for-elderly-filipinos-with-congressman-mark-go-as-author/index.html"/>
        <id>https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-11982-expanding-benefits-for-elderly-filipinos-with-congressman-mark-go-as-author/index.html</id>
            <category term="Signed into Law"/>
            <category term="Legislative Work"/>

        <updated>2024-02-02T12:12:00+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Republic Act No. 11982, signed into law on February 26, 2024, is a compassionate piece of legislation that expands the benefits provided to elderly Filipinos. Titled "An Act Granting Benefits to Filipino Octogenarians and Nonagenarians, Amending for This Purpose Republic Act No. 10868, Otherwise Known&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2> </h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>Republic Act No. 11982</strong>, signed into law on February 26, 2024, is a compassionate piece of legislation that expands the benefits provided to elderly Filipinos.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Titled "An Act Granting Benefits to Filipino Octogenarians and Nonagenarians, Amending for This Purpose Republic Act No. 10868, Otherwise Known as the 'Centenarians Act of 2016', and Appropriating Funds Therefor,"</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> the law recognizes the longevity and contributions of senior citizens by providing financial incentives to those reaching significant age milestones before becoming centenarians.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Prior to this act, only Filipinos who reached 100 years old were granted a cash gift of PHP 100,000 under the original Centenarians Act of 2016 (RA 10868). Republic Act 11982 amends this by extending a cash gift of PHP 10,000 to Filipinos upon reaching the ages of eighty (80), eighty-five (85), ninety (90), and ninety-five (95) years old.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The existing PHP 100,000 cash gift for centenarians is retained. This expansion of benefits acknowledges and celebrates the lives of a larger number of senior citizens.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Beyond the cash gifts, the act also mandates the establishment of an Elderly Data Management System to be maintained by the National Commission of Senior Citizens (NCSC).</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This system, to be developed in coordination with relevant government agencies like the Philippine Statistics Authority (PSA), the Department of Social Welfare and Development (DSWD), the Department of Information and Communications Technology (DICT), and local government units</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> (LGUs), aims to ensure the effective identification, registration, and monitoring of beneficiaries for the seamless implementation of the law.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The enactment of Republic Act 11982 is a result of consolidated legislative efforts from both the Senate and the House of Representatives. The law is a consolidation of Senate Bill No. 2028 and House Bill No. 7535, which were passed by their respective chambers on December 6, 2023.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A key figure in the passage of this significant legislation in the House of Representatives was Congressman Mark Go, the representative of the lone district of Baguio City. Congressman Go was an author of House Bill No. 7535, one of the precursor bills to Republic Act 11982. His authorship signifies his commitment to advocating for the welfare and recognition of senior citizens. By pushing for this expanded benefits package, Congressman Go and his fellow authors aimed to provide tangible support and acknowledge the valuable role that octogenarians and nonagenarians continue to play in Filipino families and society.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The funding for the implementation of Republic Act 11982 is to be included in the annual General Appropriations Act, ensuring that the necessary budget is allocated to provide the mandated cash gifts and establish the required data management system.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In summary, Republic Act 11982 is a significant stride in enhancing the welfare of elderly Filipinos by providing expanded financial benefits to octogenarians and nonagenarians. The role of Congressman Mark Go, who authored the pertinent House Bill, was crucial in championing this cause and ensuring the passage of this compassionate law that honors the nation's elderly population.</span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Republic Act 11932: Establishing the MBLISTTDA and Mark Go&#x27;s Role</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mark Go</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-11932-establishing-the-mblisttda-and-mark-gos-role/index.html"/>
        <id>https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-11932-establishing-the-mblisttda-and-mark-gos-role/index.html</id>
            <category term="Signed into Law"/>
            <category term="Legislative Work"/>

        <updated>2022-06-30T12:10:00+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Republic Act No. 11932, officially titled "An Act Creating the Metropolitan Baguio City, La Trinidad, Itogon, Sablan, Tuba, and Tublay Development Authority (MBLISTTDA), Defining Its Powers and Functions, and Providing Funds Therefor," lapsed into law on July 30, 2022. This landmark legislation addresses the need&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2> </h2>
<p><strong>Republic Act No. 11932</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">, officially titled "<strong>An Act Creating the Metropolitan Baguio City, La Trinidad, Itogon, Sablan, Tuba, and Tublay Development Authority (MBLISTTDA), Defining Its Powers and Functions, and Providing Funds Therefor,</strong>" </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">lapsed into law on July 30, 2022. This landmark legislation addresses the need for a coordinated and integrated approach to development and service delivery within the contiguous areas of Baguio City and the municipalities of La Trinidad, Itogon, Sablan, Tuba, and Tublay in Benguet, collectively known as BLISTT.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The primary purpose of RA 11932 is to establish a government instrumentality that will serve as the central planning, coordinating, and regulatory body for the MBLISTT area.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Recognizing the interconnectedness of these areas and the shared challenges they face, such as urban development, traffic management, solid waste disposal, flood control, and the provision of basic services, the Act aims to foster accelerated social, economic, and political development while respecting the autonomy of the individual local government units (LGUs).</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Key provisions of Republic Act 11932 include:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Creation of the MBLISTTDA:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Establishes the Metropolitan Baguio City, La Trinidad, Itogon, Sablan, Tuba, and Tublay Development Authority as a government instrumentality attached to the Office of the President.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Mandate and Scope of Services:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The MBLISTTDA is mandated to formulate, coordinate, and monitor policies, standards, programs, and projects that are area-wide in scope.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This includes services such as development planning, urban renewal and land use planning, transport and traffic management, solid waste disposal and management, flood control and sewerage management, water resource</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">6</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> development and management, health and sanitation, pollution control, and public safety and order.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>MBLISTT Council:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Creates a governing board and policy-making body, the MBLISTT Council, composed of the Governor of Benguet and the mayors of the component LGUs as ex officio voting members, along with representatives from relevant national government agencies.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>MBLISTTDA Administrator:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Provides for the appointment of an Administrator who will be responsible for the day-to-day operations of the Authority.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Powers and Functions:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Grants the MBLISTTDA various powers and functions necessary to carry out its mandate, including the ability to formulate plans, implement programs, promulgate rules and regulations, and coordinate with concerned LGUs and national government agencies.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Funding:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Outlines the sources of funding for the MBLISTTDA, including appropriations from the General Appropriations Act and the power to levy fines and accept grants.</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Baguio City Representative Marquez "Mark" Go was a principal author of House Bill No. 9215, the foundational bill that eventually became Republic Act 11932. He played a significant role in initiating and championing the creation of the MBLISTTDA in the House of Representatives. His authorship signifies his recognition of the need for a unified body to address the metropolitan challenges of Baguio and its surrounding </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">municipalities and his commitment toเห็นชอบ the legislative process that led to its enactment. While the Senate version of the bill would have had its own sponsors, Congressman Go's role as a principal author of the House version highlights his crucial contribution to bringing this legislation to fruition.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The establishment of the MBLISTTDA through RA 11932 is a significant step towards integrated development planning and service delivery in the BLISTT area, aiming to address common issues more effectively and promote sustainable growth for the benefit of its residents. The involvement of legislators like Mark Go from the concerned areas was instrumental in pushing for the passage of this important law.</span></p>
<p><br><br></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
