<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>markgo.org</title>
    <link href="https://www.markgo.org/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://www.markgo.org" />
    <updated>2025-05-04T12:23:22+08:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Mark Go</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://www.markgo.org</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Republic Act 11982: Expanding Benefits for Elderly Filipinos, with Congressman Mark Go as Author</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mark Go</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-11982-expanding-benefits-for-elderly-filipinos-with-congressman-mark-go-as-author/index.html"/>
        <id>https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-11982-expanding-benefits-for-elderly-filipinos-with-congressman-mark-go-as-author/index.html</id>
            <category term="Signed into Law"/>
            <category term="Legislative Work"/>

        <updated>2025-05-04T12:12:12+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Republic Act No. 11982, signed into law on February 26, 2024, is a compassionate piece of legislation that expands the benefits provided to elderly Filipinos.1 Titled "An Act Granting Benefits to Filipino Octogenarians and Nonagenarians, Amending for This Purpose Republic Act No. 10868, Otherwise Known&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2> </h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Republic Act No. 11982, signed into law on February 26, 2024, is a compassionate piece of legislation that expands the benefits provided to elderly Filipinos.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">1</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Titled "An Act Granting Benefits to Filipino Octogenarians and Nonagenarians, Amending for This Purpose Republic Act No. 10868, Otherwise Known as the 'Centenarians Act of 2016', and Appropriating Funds Therefor,"</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">2</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> the law recognizes the longevity and contributions of senior citizens by providing financial incentives to those reaching significant age milestones before becoming centenarians.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Prior to this act, only Filipinos who reached 100 years old were granted a cash gift of PHP 100,000 under the original Centenarians Act of 2016 (RA 10868). Republic Act 11982 amends this by extending a cash gift of PHP 10,000 to Filipinos upon reaching the ages of eighty (80), eighty-five (85), ninety (90), and ninety-five (95) years old.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">3</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The existing PHP 100,000 cash gift for centenarians is retained. This expansion of benefits acknowledges and celebrates the lives of a larger number of senior citizens.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Beyond the cash gifts, the act also mandates the establishment of an Elderly Data Management System to be maintained by the National Commission of Senior Citizens (NCSC).</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">4</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This system, to be developed in coordination with relevant government agencies like the Philippine Statistics Authority (PSA), the Department of Social Welfare and Development (DSWD), the Department of Information and Communications Technology (DICT), and local government units</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">5</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> (LGUs), aims to ensure the effective identification, registration, and monitoring of beneficiaries for the seamless implementation of the law.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">6</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The enactment of Republic Act 11982 is a result of consolidated legislative efforts from both the Senate and the House of Representatives. The law is a consolidation of Senate Bill No. 2028 and House Bill No. 7535, which were passed by their respective chambers on December 6, 2023.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A key figure in the passage of this significant legislation in the House of Representatives was Congressman Mark Go, the representative of the lone district of Baguio City. Congressman Go was an author of House Bill No. 7535, one of the precursor bills to Republic Act 11982. His authorship signifies his commitment to advocating for the welfare and recognition of senior citizens. By pushing for this expanded benefits package, Congressman Go and his fellow authors aimed to provide tangible support and acknowledge the valuable role that octogenarians and nonagenarians continue to play in Filipino families and society.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The funding for the implementation of Republic Act 11982 is to be included in the annual General Appropriations Act, ensuring that the necessary budget is allocated to provide the mandated cash gifts and establish the required data management system.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In summary, Republic Act 11982 is a significant stride in enhancing the welfare of elderly Filipinos by providing expanded financial benefits to octogenarians and nonagenarians. The role of legislators like Congressman Mark Go, who authored the pertinent House Bill, was crucial in championing this cause and ensuring the passage of this compassionate law that honors the nation's elderly population.</span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Republic Acts 11623 and 11624: Establishing New National High Schools in Baguio City with the Support of Congressman Mark Go</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mark Go</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.markgo.org/republic-acts-11623-and-11624-establishing-new-national-high-schools-in-baguio-city-with-the-support-of-congressman-mark-go/index.html"/>
        <id>https://www.markgo.org/republic-acts-11623-and-11624-establishing-new-national-high-schools-in-baguio-city-with-the-support-of-congressman-mark-go/index.html</id>
            <category term="Signed into Law"/>
            <category term="Legislative Work"/>

        <updated>2025-05-04T12:11:42+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Republic Acts No. 11623 and No. 11624, both enacted on December 10, 2021, are significant legislative measures that address the educational needs of specific communities within Baguio City by converting existing school annexes into independent national high schools.1 These acts facilitate improved administration and resource&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2> </h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Republic Acts No. 11623 and No. 11624, both enacted on December 10, 2021, are significant legislative measures that address the educational needs of specific communities within Baguio City by converting existing school annexes into independent national high schools.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">1</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> These acts facilitate improved administration and resource allocation for the benefit of students and educators in these areas. Congressman Mark Go, the representative of Baguio City's lone district, played a supportive role in the passage of these laws as a co-sponsor of the corresponding House Bills.</span></p>
<p><strong>Republic Act 11623: Establishing Fort Del Pilar National High School</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">2</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Republic Act 11623 is titled "AN ACT SEPARATING THE BAGUIO CITY NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL – FORT DEL PILAR ANNEX IN BARANGAY FORT DEL PILAR, BAGUIO CITY FROM THE BAGUIO CITY NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL, CONVERTING IT INTO AN INDEPENDENT NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL TO BE KNOWN AS THE FORT DEL PILAR NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL, AND APPROPRIATING FUNDS THEREFOR."</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">34</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This act effectively grants the Fort Del Pilar Annex of Baguio City National High School (BCNHS) autonomy, converting it into a standalone national high school.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">5</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The key provisions of RA 11623 include the formal separation of the annex, the transfer of all its existing personnel, assets, liabilities, and records to the newly created Fort Del Pilar National High School.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">6</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The Department of Education (DepEd) is mandated to include the operationalization of the new school in its program, with initial funding sourced from the annex's current year appropriation, and subsequent funding to be included in the annual General Appropriations Act.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">7</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This ensures dedicated resources for the school's operations and development.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The enactment of RA 11623 originated from House Bill No. 7994 in the 18th Congress. Congressman Mark Go was listed as a co-sponsor of this bill, indicating his support for the conversion of the Fort Del Pilar Annex into an independent national high school and his recognition of the need for enhanced educational facilities and administration in the area it serves.</span></p>
<p><strong>Republic Act 11624: Establishing Hillside National High School</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Similarly, Republic Act 11624 is titled "AN ACT SEPARATING THE BAGUIO CITY NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL – HILLSIDE ANNEX IN BARANGAY HILLSIDE, BAGUIO CITY FROM THE BAGUIO CITY NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL, CONVERTING IT INTO AN INDEPENDENT NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL TO BE KNOWN AS THE HILLSIDE NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL, AND APPROPRIATING FUNDS THEREFOR."</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">89</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This law mirrors the provisions of RA 11623, focusing on the Hillside Annex of BCNHS. It legally separates the Hillside Annex and converts it into the independent Hillside National High School.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">10</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The act also dictates the transfer of all personnel, assets, liabilities, and records from the annex to the new school. Like RA 11623, it directs the DepEd to facilitate the operationalization of Hillside National High School and ensures its funding through inclusion in the annual General Appropriations Act, starting with the annex's current allocation.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">11</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Republic Act 11624 originated from House Bill No. 7995 in the 18th Congress. Congressman Mark Go was also a co-sponsor of this bill. His co-sponsorship of both House Bills 7994 and 7995 demonstrates his commitment to improving the educational infrastructure and opportunities available to students in different barangays within Baguio City by supporting the independence and dedicated resourcing of these former annexes.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In conclusion, Republic Acts 11623 and 11624 are crucial legislative steps towards providing more focused and adequately supported secondary education in the Fort Del Pilar and Hillside areas of Baguio City. Congressman Mark Go's role as a co-sponsor of the foundational House Bills for both acts highlights his advocacy for enhanced educational services and his support for initiatives that directly benefit the students and communities within his district. These laws are expected to lead to improved school administration, targeted program development, and better overall learning environments in the newly established Fort Del Pilar National High School and Hillside National High School.</span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Republic Act 12118: Establishing the Baguio City High School for the Arts</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mark Go</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-12118-establishing-the-baguio-city-high-school-for-the-arts/index.html"/>
        <id>https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-12118-establishing-the-baguio-city-high-school-for-the-arts/index.html</id>
            <category term="Signed into Law"/>
            <category term="Legislative Work"/>

        <updated>2025-05-04T12:11:23+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Republic Act No. 12118, signed into law on January 3, 2025, marks a significant development in specialized secondary education in the Philippines with the establishment of the Baguio City High School for the Arts.1 This Act recognizes the importance of nurturing young Filipino talent in&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2> </h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Republic Act No. 12118, signed into law on January 3, 2025, marks a significant development in specialized secondary education in the Philippines with the establishment of the Baguio City High School for the Arts.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">1</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This Act recognizes the importance of nurturing young Filipino talent in the realm of culture and the arts.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Titled "AN ACT ESTABLISHING THE BAGUIO CITY HIGH SCHOOL FOR THE ARTS AND APPROPRIATING FUNDS THEREFOR," the law mandates the creation of a specialized public high school in Baguio City.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">2</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This institution is designed to offer an arts-focused education, providing a dedicated venue for students with exceptional aptitude and skill in various artistic disciplines to hone their craft within a structured academic environment.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">3</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Baguio City High School for the Arts will operate under the administration and supervision of the Department of Education (DepEd). It is also mandated to work in close coordination with the National Commission for Culture and the Arts (NCCA) and the Cultural Center of the Philippines (CCP).</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">4</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">5</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> collaborative framework aims to ensure that the school's curriculum and programs are aligned with national arts and culture standards and provide students with access to expertise and resources from the country's premier cultural institutions.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">6</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The establishment of this specialized high school is a testament to the State's commitment to fostering the preservation, enrichment, and dynamic evolution of Filipino national culture. By providing specialized training and education, the Act seeks to develop a new generation of artists and cultural practitioners.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">7</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The legislative journey of Republic Act 12118 began in the House of Representatives as House Bill No. 7316.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">8</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The primary author and sponsor of this foundational bill was Congressman Mark Go, the representative of the lone district of Baguio City. His leadership and advocacy were crucial in championing the establishment of a dedicated arts high school in Baguio, a city recognized for its vibrant creative scene and its designation as a UNESCO Creative City. Congressman Go's initiative underscores his commitment to providing specialized educational opportunities that cater to the diverse talents of his constituents and students from the greater Northern Luzon area.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The initial funding for the operationalization of the Baguio City High School for the Arts is charged against the current year's appropriation of the Schools Division Office of Baguio City, with subsequent funding to be included in the annual General Appropriations Act.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">9</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The DepEd, in coordination with the NCCA, CCP, and the local government of Baguio City, is tasked with promulgating the rules and regulations for the effective implementation of the Act.</span></p>
<p><strong>Congressman Mark Go's Role in Republic Acts 11623 and 11624</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Beyond his primary authorship of the law establishing the Baguio City High School for the Arts, Congressman Mark Go also played a supportive role in the enactment of two other significant education-related laws in Baguio City during the 18th Congress: Republic Act 11623 and Republic Act 11624.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Republic Act 11623, enacted on December 10, 2021, is "AN ACT SEPARATING THE BAGUIO CITY NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL – FORT DEL PILAR ANNEX IN BARANGAY FORT DEL PILAR, BAGUIO CITY FROM THE BAGUIO CITY NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL, CONVERTING IT INTO AN INDEPENDENT NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL TO BE KNOWN AS THE FORT DEL PILAR NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL, AND APPROPRIATING FUNDS THEREFOR."</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">1011</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This law effectively converted the Fort Del Pilar Annex into an independent national high school, ensuring it would have its own administration and dedicated funding.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Similarly, Republic Act 11624, also enacted on December 10, 2021, is "AN ACT SEPARATING THE BAGUIO CITY NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL – HILLSIDE ANNEX IN BARANGAY HILLSIDE, BAGUIO CITY FROM THE BAGUIO CITY NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL, CONVERTING IT INTO AN INDEPENDENT NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL TO BE KNOWN</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">12</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> AS THE HILLSIDE NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL, AND APPROPRIATING FUNDS THEREFOR."</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">1314</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This act provided the same independence and dedicated resources for the Hillside Annex, establishing it as the Hillside National High School.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Congressman Mark Go was listed as a co-sponsor of House Bill No. 7994, which led to RA 11623, and House Bill No. 7995, which led to RA 11624. His co-sponsorship of these bills demonstrates his support for the decentralization of large school annexes in his district, aiming to improve their administrative efficiency and ensure they receive adequate resources for the benefit of their students and faculty.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In summary, Congressman Mark Go has been a consistent advocate for educational advancement in Baguio City through his legislative work. His primary authorship of Republic Act 12118 paved the way for a specialized arts high school, while his co-sponsorship of the bills that became Republic Acts 11623 and 11624 contributed to the establishment of independent national high schools from former annexes, all aimed at providing better educational opportunities for the youth in his district.</span></p>
<p><br><br></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Republic Act 12119: Establishing the Baguio City Sports High School, Championed by Congressman Mark Go</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mark Go</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-12119-establishing-the-baguio-city-sports-high-school-championed-by-congressman-mark-go/index.html"/>
        <id>https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-12119-establishing-the-baguio-city-sports-high-school-championed-by-congressman-mark-go/index.html</id>
            <category term="Signed into Law"/>
            <category term="Legislative Work"/>

        <updated>2025-05-04T12:10:58+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Republic Act No. 12119, signed into law on January 3, 2025, is a significant legislative achievement for the development of sports in the Philippines, particularly in the Cordillera Administrative Region.1 Titled "AN ACT ESTABLISHING THE BAGUIO CITY SPORTS HIGH SCHOOL AND APPROPRIATING FUNDS THEREFOR," this&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2> </h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Republic Act No. 12119, signed into law on January 3, 2025, is a significant legislative achievement for the development of sports in the Philippines, particularly in the Cordillera Administrative Region.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">1</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Titled "AN ACT ESTABLISHING THE BAGUIO CITY SPORTS HIGH SCHOOL AND APPROPRIATING FUNDS THEREFOR," this law paves the way for the creation of a specialized public high school in Baguio City dedicated to nurturing young Filipino athletes.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">2</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The core principle of RA 12119 is the State's commitment to promoting physical education and sports programs to foster self-discipline, teamwork, and excellence. The Act aims to provide a dedicated educational institution that combines a standard secondary education curriculum with intensive sports training for students who have demonstrated considerable potential in various sports disciplines.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Key provisions of Republic Act 12119 include:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Establishment of the Baguio City Sports High School:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The law mandates the creation of a specialized public high school in Baguio City that will offer a sports-focused education program.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">3</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Integrated Curriculum:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The school will implement the general secondary education curriculum as prescribed by the Enhanced Basic Education Act of 2013 (RA 10533), with a significant emphasis on developing the athletic skills of learners through specialized subjects in physical education and sports.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">4</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Coordination with Sports Authorities:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The school will be administered and supervised by the Department of Education (DepEd) in close coordination with the Philippine Sports Commission</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">5</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> (PSC) and the National Academy of Sports (NAS).</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">67</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This collaboration is intended to ensure that the sports programs are aligned with national sports development goals and standards.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Funding:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The initial funding for the operationalization of the Baguio City Sports High School will be charged against the current year's appropriation of the Schools Division Office of Baguio City, with subsequent funding to be included in the annual General Appropriations Act.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">8</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The establishment of the Baguio City Sports High School is expected to provide a clear pathway for talented young athletes in Baguio and the broader Northern Luzon area to receive quality education while simultaneously developing their athletic prowess.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">9</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This specialized training is crucial for producing future national athletes who can represent the country in various competitions.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The legislative effort behind Republic Act 12119 was notably led by Congressman Mark Go, the representative of the lone district of Baguio City. He served as the primary author and sponsor of House Bill No. 8700, the precursor to this Republic Act in the House of Representatives. Congressman Go's strong advocacy for sports development and his commitment to providing specialized educational opportunities for the youth of Baguio were instrumental in the passage of this law. His initiative reflects a vision to harness the athletic potential of young Filipinos and provide them with the necessary support and training to excel in their chosen sports.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The enactment of RA 12119, alongside RA 12118 establishing the Baguio City High School for the Arts (which Congressman Go also primarily authored), signifies a concerted effort to provide specialized educational institutions in Baguio City that cater to the diverse talents and potentials of students in the region.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">10</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Congressman Go's role as the primary author and sponsor of both these landmark laws underscores his dedication to enhancing the educational landscape and providing unique opportunities for the youth in his constituency.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Department of Education, in coordination with the PSC, NAS, and the local government of Baguio City, is tasked with formulating the implementing rules and regulations for RA 12119 to ensure the effective organization, administration, operations, and management of the Baguio City Sports High School.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">11</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This will be crucial in translating the vision of the law into tangible opportunities for aspiring young athletes.</span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Republic Act 11932: Establishing the MBLISTTDA and Mark Go&#x27;s Role</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mark Go</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-11932-establishing-the-mblisttda-and-mark-gos-role/index.html"/>
        <id>https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-11932-establishing-the-mblisttda-and-mark-gos-role/index.html</id>
            <category term="Signed into Law"/>
            <category term="Legislative Work"/>

        <updated>2025-05-04T12:10:39+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Republic Act No. 11932, officially titled "An Act Creating the Metropolitan Baguio City, La Trinidad, Itogon, Sablan, Tuba, and Tublay Development Authority (MBLISTTDA), Defining Its Powers and Functions, and Providing Funds Therefor,"1 lapsed into law on July 30, 2022. This landmark legislation addresses the need&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2> </h2>
<p><strong>Republic Act No. 11932</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">, officially titled "An Act Creating the Metropolitan Baguio City, La Trinidad, Itogon, Sablan, Tuba, and Tublay Development Authority (MBLISTTDA), Defining Its Powers and Functions, and Providing Funds Therefor,"</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">1</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> lapsed into law on July 30, 2022. This landmark legislation addresses the need for a coordinated and integrated approach to development and service delivery within the contiguous areas of Baguio City and the municipalities of La Trinidad, Itogon, Sablan, Tuba, and Tublay in Benguet, collectively known as BLISTT.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The primary purpose of RA 11932 is to establish a government instrumentality that will serve as the central planning, coordinating, and regulatory body for the MBLISTT area.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">2</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Recognizing the interconnectedness of these areas and the shared challenges they face, such as urban development, traffic management, solid waste disposal, flood control, and the provision of basic services, the Act aims to foster accelerated social, economic, and political development while respecting the autonomy of the individual local government units (LGUs).</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">3</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Key provisions of Republic Act 11932 include:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Creation of the MBLISTTDA:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Establishes the Metropolitan Baguio City, La Trinidad, Itogon, Sablan, Tuba, and Tublay Development Authority as a government instrumentality attached to the Office of the President.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">4</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Mandate and Scope of Services:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The MBLISTTDA is mandated to formulate, coordinate, and monitor policies, standards, programs, and projects that are area-wide in scope.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">5</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This includes services such as development planning, urban renewal and land use planning, transport and traffic management, solid waste disposal and management, flood control and sewerage management, water resource</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">6</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> development and management, health and sanitation, pollution control, and public safety and order.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">7</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>MBLISTT Council:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Creates a governing board and policy-making body, the MBLISTT Council, composed of the Governor of Benguet and the mayors of the component LGUs as ex officio voting members, along with representatives from relevant national government agencies.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">8</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>MBLISTTDA Administrator:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Provides for the appointment of an Administrator who will be responsible for the day-to-day operations of the Authority.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">9</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Powers and Functions:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Grants the MBLISTTDA various powers and functions necessary to carry out its mandate, including the ability to formulate plans, implement programs, promulgate rules and regulations, and coordinate with concerned LGUs and national government agencies.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">10</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Funding:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Outlines the sources of funding for the MBLISTTDA, including appropriations from the General Appropriations Act and the power to levy fines and accept grants.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">11</span></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Mark Go's Role</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Based on legislative records, then Baguio City Representative Marquez "Mark" Go was a principal author of House Bill No. 9215, the foundational bill that eventually became Republic Act 11932. This indicates that he played a significant role in initiating and championing the creation of the MBLISTTDA in the House of Representatives. His authorship signifies his recognition of the need for a unified body to address the metropolitan challenges of Baguio and its surrounding</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">municipalities and his commitment toเห็นชอบ the legislative process that led to its enactment. While the Senate version of the bill would have had its own sponsors, Congressman Go's role as a principal author of the House version highlights his crucial contribution to bringing this legislation to fruition.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The establishment of the MBLISTTDA through RA 11932 is a significant step towards integrated development planning and service delivery in the BLISTT area, aiming to address common issues more effectively and promote sustainable growth for the benefit of its residents. The involvement of legislators like Mark Go from the concerned areas was instrumental in pushing for the passage of this important law.</span></p>
<p><br><br></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Republic Act 11604: Mandating the Full Rehabilitation and Maintenance of Kennon Road</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mark Go</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-11604-mandating-the-full-rehabilitation-and-maintenance-of-kennon-road/index.html"/>
        <id>https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-11604-mandating-the-full-rehabilitation-and-maintenance-of-kennon-road/index.html</id>
            <category term="Signed into Law"/>
            <category term="Legislative Work"/>

        <updated>2025-05-04T12:10:08+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Republic Act No. 11604, signed into law on December 10, 2021, is a significant piece of legislation that specifically addresses the long-standing issues concerning Kennon Road, a critical artery connecting Baguio City to the lowlands of La Union and other parts of Luzon.1 Titled "An&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2> </h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Republic Act No. 11604, signed into law on December 10, 2021, is a significant piece of legislation that specifically addresses the long-standing issues concerning </span><strong>Kennon Road</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">, a critical artery connecting Baguio City to the lowlands of La Union and other parts of Luzon.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">1</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Titled "An Act Mandating the Full Rehabilitation and Maintenance of Kennon Road Under the Department of Public Works and Highways,"</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">2</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> the law places the primary responsibility for the road's upkeep and improvement squarely on the shoulders of the national government, through the Department of Public Works and Highways (DPWH).</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">3</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The enactment of RA 11604 stems from the persistent challenges faced by Kennon Road, including its susceptibility to landslides and closures, particularly during the rainy season.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">4</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> These issues have significantly impacted transportation, commerce, and tourism in the Baguio and the Cordillera Administrative Region.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">5</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The main provisions of Republic Act 11604 include:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Mandating Full Rehabilitation:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The Act directs the DPWH to undertake the complete rehabilitation of the entire 33.534-kilometer stretch of Kennon Road, from Rosario, La Union, to Baguio City.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">6</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This rehabilitation is expected to involve necessary engineering interventions to improve the road's structural integrity and resilience against natural calamities.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">7</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Responsibility for Maintenance:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Following the rehabilitation, the DPWH is also mandated to be solely responsible for the continuous maintenance of Kennon Road.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">8</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This ensures that the road remains safe, well-maintained, and optimally serviceable for travelers.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Funding Allocation:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The necessary funds for both the rehabilitation and subsequent maintenance of Kennon Road are to be included in the annual General Appropriations Act (GAA).</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">9</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This provision aims to ensure dedicated and consistent funding for the crucial road, moving away from potentially sporadic or insufficient allocations.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Evaluation and Feasibility Study:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The DPWH, in coordination with the Department of Environment and Natural Resources (DENR) Cordillera Regional Office, is required to evaluate the current condition of Kennon Road and conduct a feasibility study.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">10</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This study will inform the planning and implementation of the rehabilitation efforts, with the goal of transforming Kennon Road into an "all-weather" road.</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">By centralizing the responsibility for Kennon Road under the DPWH and guaranteeing annual funding through the GAA, Republic Act 11604 seeks to provide a long-term solution to the road's perennial problems, aiming for a more reliable and safer passage for commuters and goods traversing this vital link.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">11</span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Republic Act 11509: The Doktor Para sa Bayan Act</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mark Go</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-11509-the-doktor-para-sa-bayan-act/index.html"/>
        <id>https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-11509-the-doktor-para-sa-bayan-act/index.html</id>
            <category term="Signed into Law"/>
            <category term="Legislative Work"/>

        <updated>2025-05-04T12:09:41+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Republic Act No. 11509, also known as the "Doktor Para sa Bayan Act," is a significant Philippine law enacted on December 23, 2020.1 This Act establishes a Medical Scholarship and Return Service Program aimed at addressing the persistent lack of doctors in the country, particularly&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2> </h2>
<p><strong>Republic Act No. 11509</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">, also known as the "</span><strong>Doktor Para sa Bayan Act</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">," is a significant Philippine law enacted on December 23, 2020.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">1</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This Act establishes a Medical Scholarship and Return Service Program aimed at addressing the persistent lack of doctors in the country, particularly in underserved and rural areas.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">2</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The core purpose of the Doktor Para sa Bayan Act is to incentivize deserving Filipino students to pursue a Doctor of Medicine degree by providing them with financial assistance and, in return, requiring them to render service in government public health offices or hospitals upon becoming licensed physicians.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">3</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This mechanism seeks to produce aSaya of doctors who are committed to serving the health needs of underprivileged communities and ultimately improve the doctor-to-population ratio across the archipelago.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Key provisions of Republic Act 11509 include:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Establishment of the Medical Scholarship and Return Service Program (MSRS):</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The Act mandates the creation of a scholarship program for deserving students in State Universities and Colleges (SUCs) or in partner private Higher Education Institutions (PHEIs) in regions where</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">4</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> no SUCs offer a medical course.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">56</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Prioritization of Deserving Students:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The program prioritizes qualified applicants from municipalities without government physicians to ensure that these underserved areas will eventually have access to medical doctors.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">7</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Comprehensive Financial Assistance:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The scholarship program covers various expenses, including free tuition and other school fees, allowances for books, supplies, equipment, clothing, dormitory or boarding house accommodation, transportation, internship fees, medical board review fees, license fees, annual medical insurance, and other education-related miscellaneous and living allowances.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Qualification Requirements:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Applicants must be Filipino citizens residing in the Philippines, be a graduating student or a graduate of an appropriate undergraduate program, have passed the required entrance examinations and complied with admission requirements of the medical school, and have obtained the mandated National Medical Admission Test (NMAT) score.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">8</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Mandatory Return Service:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> A crucial component of the scholarship is the mandatory return service.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">9</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Upon passing the Physician Licensure Examination and obtaining their license, scholars are required to serve in a government public health office, government hospital, or any accredited government health facility</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">10</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> in their hometown or an underserved municipality.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">11</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The duration of the return service is proportionate to the length of the scholarship availed.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Integration into the Public Health System:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The Act facilitates the integration of scholars into the public health and medical service system through the Department of Health (DOH), ensuring they receive appropriate civil service ranks and compensation during their return service.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">12</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Formulation of Implementing Rules and Regulations (IRR):</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The Commission on Higher Education (CHED) and the DOH are mandated to jointly formulate and issue the IRR to ensure the effective implementation of the Act.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">13</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Sanctions:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The Act includes provisions for sanctions for failure to comply with the mandatory return service obligation, which may include the repayment of the scholarship cost and other penalties.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">14</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Doktor Para sa Bayan Act is a crucial step towards strengthening the healthcare system in the Philippines by addressing the shortage of medical professionals and promoting equitable access to healthcare services, particularly in remote and underserved areas.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">15</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> It provides a pathway for aspiring doctors from various backgrounds to pursue medical education and contribute to the well-being of their communities.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">16</span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Republic Act 11032: The Ease of Doing Business and Efficient Government Service Delivery Act of 2018</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mark Go</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-11032-the-ease-of-doing-business-and-efficient-government-service-delivery-act-of-2018/index.html"/>
        <id>https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-11032-the-ease-of-doing-business-and-efficient-government-service-delivery-act-of-2018/index.html</id>
            <category term="Signed into Law"/>
            <category term="Legislative Work"/>

        <updated>2025-05-04T12:09:06+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Republic Act No. 11032, officially known as the "Ease of Doing Business and Efficient Government Service Delivery Act of 2018," is a landmark legislation in the Philippines that significantly amended the Anti-Red Tape Act of 2007.1 Enacted on May 28, 2018, and becoming effective on&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2> </h2>
<p><strong>Republic Act No. 11032</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">, officially known as the "</span><strong>Ease of Doing Business and Efficient Government Service Delivery Act of 2018</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">," is a landmark legislation in the Philippines that significantly amended the Anti-Red Tape Act of 2007.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">1</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Enacted on May 28, 2018, and becoming effective on June 17, 2018, this Act is a cornerstone of the Philippine government's efforts to improve the business environment and enhance the efficiency of government service delivery.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">2</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The primary purpose of RA 11032 is to streamline government transactions for both business and non-business related purposes.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">3</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> It aims to reduce bureaucratic red tape, eliminate corruption, and ultimately create a more favorable climate for both local and foreign investors, as well as improve the overall experience of citizens when transacting with government agencies.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">4</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Key provisions and features of Republic Act 11032 include:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Prescribed Processing Times:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The Act sets specific maximum processing times for government transactions:</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">5</span></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="2"><strong>Simple transactions:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Must be completed within three (3) working days.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="2"><strong>Complex transactions:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Must be completed within seven (7) working days.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="2"><strong>Highly technical transactions or those involving activities that pose a danger to public health, safety, morals, public policy, and environment:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Must be completed within twenty (20) working days.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">6</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> These timeframes exclude the मेयर of the application or request.</span></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Citizen's Charter: All government agencies are required to adopt and7</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">prominently display their Citizen's Charter. This document should provide</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">detailed information about the services offered, including a comprehensive</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">checklist of requirements, the step-by-step procedure, the person</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">responsible for each step, the maximum processing time, the fees, and</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">mechanisms for feedback and complaints.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Zero Contact Policy: The Act promotes a "Zero Contact Policy,"8</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">limiting face-to-face interaction between applicants or requesting parties9</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">and government officers or employees during the processing of transactions,</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">except during the preliminary assessment or when strictly necessary. This</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">measure aims to minimize opportunities for corruption.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Creation of the Anti-Red Tape Authority (ARTA): RA 11032</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">established the ARTA as the primary government agency</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">responsible for the national policy on anti-red tape and ease of doing</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">business. ARTA is mandated to monitor and10</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">ensure compliance of government agencies,</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">implement reform initiatives, and investigate</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">violations of the Act.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Automated Business Permitting and Licensing Systems: The Act</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">mandates LGUs to automate their business permitting and licensing systems11</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">to create a single business permit application form and establish a Business12</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">One-Stop Shop (BOSS) to facilitate faster processing.13</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Central Business Portal and Philippine Business Databank: The Act</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">directs the Department of Information and Communications Technology (DICT)</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">to establish a Central Business Portal for online business registration</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">and a Philippine Business Databank to serve as a central repository of</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">business information accessible to government agencies.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Accountability and Penalties: The Act outlines administrative and</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">criminal liabilities for government officials and employees who violate its</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">provisions, including prescribed processing times and the anti-red tape14</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">regulations. Penalties range from suspension to dismissal from service,15</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">fines, and imprisonment.</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In essence, Republic Act 11032 is a comprehensive reform measure designed to cut down on bureaucratic delays and complexities that have long been aimpediment to efficient governance and business growth in the Philippines. By setting clear standards, promoting transparency, leveraging technology, and imposing stricter accountability, the Act aims to create a more efficient,16</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">transparent, and corruption-free environment for all those who interact with government services.</span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Republic Act 11984: Ending the &quot;No Permit, No Exam&quot; Policy for Disadvantaged Students</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mark Go</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-11984-ending-the-no-permit-no-exam-policy-for-disadvantaged-students/index.html"/>
        <id>https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-11984-ending-the-no-permit-no-exam-policy-for-disadvantaged-students/index.html</id>
            <category term="Signed into Law"/>
            <category term="Legislative Work"/>

        <updated>2025-05-04T12:08:40+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Republic Act No. 11984, officially titled the "No Permit, No Exam Prohibition Act," is a significant piece of legislation in the Philippines that was approved on March 11, 2024.1 This Act directly addresses a long-standing issue in the Philippine education system where students with unsettled&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2> </h2>
<p><strong>Republic Act No. 11984</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">, officially titled the "</span><strong>No Permit, No Exam Prohibition Act</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">," is a significant piece of legislation in the Philippines that was approved on March 11, 2024.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">1</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This Act directly addresses a long-standing issue in the Philippine education system where students with unsettled tuition and other school fees are barred from taking their periodic and final examinations.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">2</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The core purpose of RA 11984 is to protect and promote the right of disadvantaged students to quality education by ensuring that their inability to immediately pay their school fees does not become a barrier to taking scheduled examinations.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">3</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The State recognizes the importance of education and aims to make it more accessible, particularly for those facing financial difficulties.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Key provisions of Republic Act 11984 include:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Prohibition of the "No Permit, No Exam" Policy:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The Act explicitly prohibits all public and private educational institutions, including basic education (K to 12), higher education institutions (HEIs), and technical-vocational institutions (TVIs) offering long-term courses (exceeding one year), from preventing disadvantaged students with unpaid tuition and other school fees from taking their periodic and final examinations.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">4</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Mandate to Accommodate Disadvantaged Students:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Educational institutions covered by the Act are mandated to accommodate and allow these disadvantaged students to take their examinations without requiring a permit. For K to 12 students, this mandate applies for the entire school year.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Definition of "Disadvantaged Student":</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The Act directs the Department of Social Welfare and Development (DSWD), in consultation with relevant stakeholders, to promulgate the rules and regulations that will define what constitutes a "Disadvantaged Student" and the criteria and requirements for the issuance of a certification to that effect by the appropriate local social welfare development officer.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">5</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This aims to provide a clear basis for identifying students covered by the Act.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Administrative Sanctions:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Educational institutions found violating the provisions of the Act will be subject to administrative sanctions imposed by the relevant government agencies, namely the Department of Education (DepEd), the Commission on Higher Education (CHED), and the Technical Education and Skills Development Authority (TESDA),</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">6</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> as the case may be.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">7</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Preservation of Institutions' Right to Collect Fees:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> While the Act prohibits barring students from exams, it clarifies that it is without prejudice to the right and power of educational institutions to require the submission of a promissory note, withhold</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">8</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> the release of student records and credentials, and pursue other legal and administrative remedies to collect unpaid fees.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">9</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In essence, Republic Act 11984 provides a legal safety net for disadvantaged students, ensuring that they are not denied the opportunity to be assessed academically solely due to financial constraints at the time of examinations.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">10</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> It reinforces the constitutional right to education and emphasizes compassion and understanding for students facing economic hardships, while still acknowledging the right of educational institutions to seek payment of arrears through other legitimate means.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">11</span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Republic Act 12077: Providing Relief on Student Loan Payments During Calamities</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mark Go</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-12077-providing-relief-on-student-loan-payments-during-calamities/index.html"/>
        <id>https://www.markgo.org/republic-act-12077-providing-relief-on-student-loan-payments-during-calamities/index.html</id>
            <category term="Signed into Law"/>
            <category term="Legislative Work"/>

        <updated>2025-05-04T12:08:20+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Republic Act No. 12077, also known as the "Student Loan Payment Moratorium During Disasters and Emergencies Act," is a recently enacted Philippine law approved on December 6, 2024.1 This Act provides much-needed financial relief to students and their families who are grappling with the aftermath&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2> </h2>
<p><strong>Republic Act No. 12077</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">, also known as the "</span><strong>Student Loan Payment Moratorium During Disasters and Emergencies Act</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">," is a recently enacted Philippine law approved on December 6, 2024.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">1</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This Act provides much-needed financial relief to students and their families who are grappling with the aftermath of disasters and other emergencies.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">2</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The core purpose of RA 12077 is to alleviate the financial burden on students with outstanding loans during times of crisis.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">3</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Recognizing that natural calamities and other emergencies can severely impact the capacity of students and their families to meet their financial obligations, the State has mandated a temporary suspension of student loan payments to allow them to prioritize recovery and rebuilding their lives.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">4</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Key provisions of Republic Act 12077 include:</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Mandatory Moratorium:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The Act provides for a mandatory moratorium on the payment of all fees, charges, and costs related to student loans.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">5</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Coverage:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This moratorium applies to students enrolled in State Universities and Colleges (SUCs), Local Universities and Colleges (LUCs), private Higher Education Institutions (HEIs), and</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">6</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> public and private Technical-Vocational Institutions (TVIs). The student's residence must be located in a barangay, municipality, city, province, or region under a State of Calamity or State of Emergency as declared by the President of the Philippines or the local sanggunian.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Covered Loans:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The moratorium covers student loans incurred for higher education and technical-vocational education and training (TVET) programs, regardless of whether they are administered by the educational institutions themselves or by government entities such as the Unified Student Financial Assistance System for Tertiary Education (UniFAST) Board or the Commission on Higher Education (CHED).</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">7</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>No Penalties or Additional Interest:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Crucially, the Act stipulates that no penalties, surcharges, or additional interest shall be imposed on the outstanding student loans during the period of the moratorium.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">8</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><strong>Duration of the Moratorium:</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The moratorium will be in effect for a reasonable period during and after the onset of the disaster or emergency, as defined by the appropriate authorities and the implementing rules and regulations of the Act.</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">By enacting RA 12077, the Philippine government demonstrates its commitment to supporting students and ensuring that their pursuit of education is not derailed by unforeseen crises.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">9</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> This law provides a vital safety net, offering temporary financial respite to those most affected by disasters and allowing them to focus on recovery without the added pressure of immediate loan repayments.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">10</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> The implementation of this Act is expected to provide significant relief to countless students and families in times of great need.</span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
